<!-- 
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
#              C E D A R
#          S O L U T I O N S       "Software done right."
#           S O F T W A R E
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
# Copyright (c) 2005-2008,2010,2015 Kenneth J. Pronovici.
# All rights reserved.
#
# This work is free; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
# under the terms of the GNU General Public License, Version 2,
# as published by the Free Software Foundation.
#
# This work is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
#
# Copies of the GNU General Public License are available from
# the Free Software Foundation website, http://www.gnu.org/.
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
# Author   : Kenneth J. Pronovici <pronovic@ieee.org>
# Language : O'Reilly DocBook Lite XML DTD
# Project  : Cedar Backup, release 3
# Purpose  : Cedar Backup software manual, Installation chapter.
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
-->

<chapter id="cedar-install">

   <title>Installation</title>

   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-install-background">
         
      <title>Background</title>

      <para>
         There are two different ways to install Cedar Backup.  The easiest way
         is to install the pre-built Debian packages.  This method is painless
         and ensures that all of the correct dependencies are available, etc.
      </para>

      <para>
         If you are running a Linux distribution other than Debian or you are
         running some other platform like FreeBSD or Mac OS X, then you must use the
         Python source distribution to install Cedar Backup.  When using this
         method, you need to manage all of the dependencies yourself.
      </para>

      <sidebar>

         <title>Non-Linux Platforms</title>

         <para>
            Cedar Backup has been developed on a Debian GNU/Linux system and is
            primarily supported on Debian and other Linux systems.  However,
            since it is written in portable Python, it should run without
            problems on just about any UNIX-like operating system.  In
            particular, full Cedar Backup functionality is known to work on
            Debian and SuSE Linux systems, and client functionality is also
            known to work on FreeBSD and Mac OS X systems.
         </para>

         <para>
            To run a Cedar Backup client, you really just need a working Python
            installation.  To run a Cedar Backup master, you will also need a set
            of other executables, most of which are related to building and
            writing CD/DVD images.  A full list of dependencies is provided further
            on in this chapter.
         </para>

      </sidebar>

   </sect1>

   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-install-debian">
         
      <title>Installing on a Debian System</title>

      <para>
         The easiest way to install Cedar Backup onto a Debian system is by
         using a tool such as <command>apt-get</command> or
         <command>aptitude</command>.
      </para>

      <para>
         If you are running a Debian release which contains Cedar Backup, you
         can use your normal Debian mirror as an APT data source. (The Debian
         <quote>etch</quote> release is the first release to contain Cedar
         Backup.) Otherwise, you need to install from the Cedar Solutions APT
         data source.  To do this, add the Cedar Solutions APT data source to
         your <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> file.  
      </para>

      <para>
         After you have configured the proper APT data source, install Cedar
         Backup using this set of commands:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ apt-get update
$ apt-get install cedar-backup3 cedar-backup3-doc
      </screen>

      <para>
         Several of the Cedar Backup dependencies are listed as
         <quote>recommended</quote> rather than required.  If you are
         installing Cedar Backup on a master machine, you must install some or
         all of the recommended dependencies, depending on which actions you
         intend to execute.  The stage action normally requires ssh, and the
         store action requires eject and either cdrecord/mkisofs or
         dvd+rw-tools.  Clients must also install some sort of ssh
         server if a remote master will collect backups from them.
      </para>

      <para>
         If you would prefer, you can also download the
         <filename>.deb</filename> files and install them by hand with a tool
         such as <command>dpkg</command>.  You can find 
         these files files in the Cedar Solutions APT source.
         <footnote id="cedar-install-foot-software"><para>See <ulink
         url="http://cedar-solutions.com/debian.html"/>.</para></footnote>
      </para>

      <para>
         In either case, once the package has been installed, you can proceed
         to configuration as described in <xref linkend="cedar-config"/>.
      </para>

      <note>
         <para>
            The Debian package-management tools must generally be run as root.
            It is safe to install Cedar Backup to a non-standard location and
            run it as a non-root user.  However, to do this, you must install
            the source distribution instead of the Debian package.
         </para>
      </note>

   </sect1>

   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-install-source">
         
      <title>Installing from Source</title>

      <para>
         On platforms other than Debian, Cedar Backup is installed from a
         Python source distribution. <footnote><para>See <ulink
         url="http://docs.python.org/lib/module-distutils.html"/>
         .</para></footnote> You will have to manage dependencies on your own.
      </para>

      <tip>
         <para>
            Many UNIX-like distributions provide an automatic or semi-automatic
            way to install packages like the ones Cedar Backup requires (think
            RPMs for Mandrake or RedHat, Gentoo's Portage system, the Fink
            project for Mac OS X, or the BSD ports system).  If you are not
            sure how to install these packages on your system, you might want
            to check out <xref linkend="cedar-depends"/>.  This appendix
            provides links to <quote>upstream</quote> source packages, plus as
            much information as I have been able to gather about packages for
            non-Debian platforms.
         </para>
      </tip>

      <!-- ################################################################# -->

      <sect2 id="cedar-install-source-deps">
                  
         <title>Installing Dependencies</title>

         <para>
            Cedar Backup requires a number of external packages in order to
            function properly.  Before installing Cedar Backup, you must make
            sure that these dependencies are met.  
         </para>

         <para>
            Cedar Backup is written in Python and requires version 3.4 or
            greater of the language.  You must install Python 3 on every peer
            node in a pool (master or client). 
         </para>

         <para>
            Additionally, remote client peer nodes must be running an
            <firstterm>RSH-compatible</firstterm> server, such as the
            <command>ssh</command> server, and master nodes must have an
            RSH-compatible client installed if they need to connect to remote
            peer machines.
         </para>

         <para>
            Master machines also require several other system utilities, most
            having to do with writing and validating CD/DVD media.  On master
            machines, you must make sure that these utilities are available if
            you want to to run the store action:
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><command>mkisofs</command></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><command>eject</command></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><command>mount</command></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><command>unmount</command></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><command>volname</command></para></listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
          
         <para>
            Then, you need this utility if you are writing CD media:
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><command>cdrecord</command></para></listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            <emphasis>or</emphasis> these utilities if you are writing DVD
            media:
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><command>growisofs</command></para></listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            All of these utilities are common and are easy to find for almost
            any UNIX-like operating system.
         </para>

      </sect2>

      <!-- ################################################################# -->

      <sect2 id="cedar-install-source-package">
                  
         <title>Installing the Source Package</title>

         <para>
            Python source packages are fairly easy to install.  They are
            distributed as <filename>.tar.gz</filename> files which contain
            Python source code, a manifest and an installation script called
            <filename>setup.py</filename>.  
         </para>

         <para>
            Once you have downloaded the source package from the Cedar
            Solutions website, <footnoteref
            linkend="cedar-install-foot-software"/> untar it:
         </para>

         <screen>
$ zcat CedarBackup3-2.0.0.tar.gz | tar xvf -
         </screen>

         <para>
            This will create a directory called (in this case)
            <filename>CedarBackup3-2.0.0</filename>.  The version number in the
            directory will always match the version number in the filename.
         </para>

         <para>
            If you have root access and want to install the package to the
            <quote>standard</quote> Python location on your system, then you
            can install the package in two simple steps:
         </para>

         <screen>
$ cd CedarBackup3-2.0.0
$ python setup.py install
         </screen>

         <para>
            Make sure that you are using Python 3.4 or better to execute
            <filename>setup.py</filename>.
         </para>

         <para>
            You may also wish to run the unit tests before actually installing
            anything.  Run them like so:
         </para>

         <screen>
python util/test.py
         </screen>

         <para>
            If any unit test reports a failure on your system, please email me the
            output from the unit test, so I can fix the problem.
            <footnote><para><email>support@cedar-solutions.com</email></para></footnote>
            This is particularly important for non-Linux platforms where I do
            not have a test system available to me.
         </para>

         <para>
            Some users might want to choose a different install location or
            change other install parameters.  To get more information about how
            <filename>setup.py</filename> works, use the
            <option>--help</option> option:
         </para>

         <screen>
$ python setup.py --help
$ python setup.py install --help
         </screen>

         <para>
            In any case, once the package has been installed, you can proceed
            to configuration as described in <xref linkend="cedar-config"/>.
         </para>

      </sect2>

   </sect1>

</chapter>

