<!--
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
#              C E D A R
#          S O L U T I O N S       "Software done right."
#           S O F T W A R E
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
# Copyright (c) 2007,2010,2015 Kenneth J. Pronovici.
# All rights reserved.
#
# This work is free; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
# under the terms of the GNU General Public License, Version 2,
# as published by the Free Software Foundation.
#
# This work is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
#
# Copies of the GNU General Public License are available from
# the Free Software Foundation website, http://www.gnu.org/.
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
# Author   : Kenneth J. Pronovici <pronovic@ieee.org>
# Language : O'Reilly DocBook Lite XML DTD
# Project  : Cedar Backup, release 3
# Purpose  : Cedar Backup Software Manual, securing SSH appendix.
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
-->

<appendix id="cedar-securingssh">

   <title>Securing Password-less SSH Connections</title>

   <simplesect>

      <para>
         Cedar Backup relies on password-less public key SSH connections to
         make various parts of its backup process work.  Password-less
         <command>scp</command> is used to stage files from remote clients to
         the master, and password-less <command>ssh</command> is used to
         execute actions on managed clients.  
      </para>
         
      <para>
         Normally, it is a good idea to avoid password-less SSH connections in
         favor of using an SSH agent.  The SSH agent manages your SSH
         connections so that you don't need to type your passphrase over and
         over.  You get most of the benefits of a password-less connection
         without the risk.  Unfortunately, because Cedar Backup has to execute
         without human involvement (through a cron job), use of an agent really
         isn't feasable.  We have to rely on true password-less public keys to
         give the master access to the client peers.
      </para>

      <para>
         Traditionally, Cedar Backup has relied on a <quote>segmenting</quote>
         strategy to minimize the risk.  Although the backup typically runs as
         root &mdash; so that all parts of the filesystem can be backed up
         &mdash; we don't use the root user for network connections.  Instead,
         we use a dedicated backup user on the master to initiate network
         connections, and dedicated users on each of the remote peers to accept
         network connections.
      </para>

      <para>
         With this strategy in place, an attacker with access to the backup
         user on the master (or even root access, really) can at best only get
         access to the backup user on the remote peers.  We still concede a
         local attack vector, but at least that vector is restricted to an
         unprivileged user.
      </para>

      <para>
         Some Cedar Backup users may not be comfortable with this risk, and
         others may not be able to implement the segmentation strategy &mdash;
         they simply may not have a way to create a login which is only used
         for backups.
      </para>

      <para>
         So, what are these users to do?  Fortunately there is a solution.
         The SSH authorized keys file supports a way to put a <quote>filter</quote>
         in place on an SSH connection.  This excerpt is from the AUTHORIZED_KEYS FILE FORMAT
         section of man 8 sshd:
      </para>

      <screen>
command="command"
   Specifies that the command is executed whenever this key is used for
   authentication.  The command supplied by the user (if any) is ignored.  The
   command is run on a pty if the client requests a pty; otherwise it is run
   without a tty.  If an 8-bit clean channel is required, one must not request
   a pty or should specify no-pty.  A quote may be included in the command by
   quoting it with a backslash.  This option might be useful to restrict
   certain public keys to perform just a specific operation.  An example might
   be a key that permits remote backups but nothing else.  Note that the client
   may specify TCP and/or X11 forwarding unless they are explicitly prohibited.
   Note that this option applies to shell, command or subsystem execution.
      </screen>

      <para>
         Essentially, this gives us a way to authenticate the commands that are
         being executed.  We can either accept or reject commands, and we can
         even provide a readable error message for commands we reject.  The
         filter is applied on the remote peer, to the key that provides the
         master access to the remote peer.  
      </para>

      <para>
         So, let's imagine that we have two hosts: master
         <quote>mickey</quote>, and peer <quote>minnie</quote>.  Here is the
         original <filename>~/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename> file for the
         backup user on minnie (remember, this is all on one line in the file):
      </para>

      <screen>
ssh-rsa AAAAB3NzaC1yc2EAAAABIwAAAIEAxw7EnqVULBFgPcut3WYp3MsSpVB9q9iZ+awek120391k;mm0c221=3=km
=m=askdalkS82mlF7SusBTcXiCk1BGsg7axZ2sclgK+FfWV1Jm0/I9yo9FtAZ9U+MmpL901231asdkl;ai1-923ma9s=9=
1-2341=-a0sd=-sa0=1z= backup@mickey
      </screen>

      <para>
         This line is the public key that minnie can use to identify the backup
         user on mickey.  Assuming that there is no passphrase on the private
         key back on mickey, the backup user on mickey can get direct access to
         minnie.
      </para>

      <para>
         To put the filter in place, we add a command option to the key,
         like this:
      </para>

      <screen>
command="/opt/backup/validate-backup" ssh-rsa AAAAB3NzaC1yc2EAAAABIwAAAIEAxw7EnqVULBFgPcut3WYp
3MsSpVB9q9iZ+awek120391k;mm0c221=3=km=m=askdalkS82mlF7SusBTcXiCk1BGsg7axZ2sclgK+FfWV1Jm0/I9yo9F
tAZ9U+MmpL901231asdkl;ai1-923ma9s=9=1-2341=-a0sd=-sa0=1z= backup@mickey
      </screen>

      <para>
         Basically, the command option says that whenever this key is used
         to successfully initiate a connection, the
         <command>/opt/backup/validate-backup</command> command will be run
         <emphasis>instead of</emphasis> the real command that came over the
         SSH connection.  Fortunately, the interface gives the command access
         to certain shell variables that can be used to invoke the original
         command if you want to.
      </para>

      <para>
         A very basic <command>validate-backup</command> script might look
         something like this:
      </para>

      <screen>
#!/bin/bash
if [[ "${SSH_ORIGINAL_COMMAND}" == "ls -l" ]] ; then
    ${SSH_ORIGINAL_COMMAND}
else
   echo "Security policy does not allow command [${SSH_ORIGINAL_COMMAND}]."
   exit 1
fi
      </screen>

      <para>
         This script allows exactly <command>ls -l</command> and nothing else.
         If the user attempts some other command, they get a nice error message
         telling them that their command has been disallowed.  
      </para>
         
      <para>
         For remote commands executed over <command>ssh</command>, the original
         command is exactly what the caller attempted to invoke.  For remote
         copies, the commands are either <command>scp -f file</command> (copy
         <emphasis>from</emphasis> the peer to the master) or <command>scp -t
         file</command> (copy <emphasis>to</emphasis> the peer from the
         master).  
      </para>
         
      <para>
         If you want, you can see what command SSH thinks it is executing by
         using <command>ssh -v</command> or <command>scp -v</command>.  The
         command will be right at the top, something like this:
      </para>

      <screen>
Executing: program /usr/bin/ssh host mickey, user (unspecified), command scp -v -f .profile
OpenSSH_4.3p2 Debian-9, OpenSSL 0.9.8c 05 Sep 2006
debug1: Reading configuration data /home/backup/.ssh/config
debug1: Applying options for daystrom
debug1: Reading configuration data /etc/ssh/ssh_config
debug1: Applying options for *
debug2: ssh_connect: needpriv 0
      </screen>

      <para>
         Omit the <command>-v</command> and you have your command: <command>scp
         -f .profile</command>.
      </para>

      <para>
         For a normal, non-managed setup, you need to allow the following
         commands, where <filename>/path/to/collect/</filename> is replaced
         with the real path to the collect directory on the remote peer:
      </para>

      <screen>
scp -f /path/to/collect/cback.collect
scp -f /path/to/collect/*
scp -t /path/to/collect/cback.stage
      </screen>

      <para>
         If you are configuring a managed client, then you also need to list
         the exact command lines that the master will be invoking on the
         managed client.  You are guaranteed that the master will invoke one
         action at a time, so if you list two lines per action (full and
         non-full) you should be fine.  Here's an example for the collect
         action:
      </para>

      <screen>
/usr/bin/cback3 --full collect
/usr/bin/cback3 collect
      </screen>

      <para>
         Of course, you would have to list the actual path to the
         <command>cback3</command> executable &mdash; exactly the one listed in
         the &lt;cback_command&gt; configuration option for your managed peer.
      </para>

      <para>
         I hope that there is enough information here for interested users to
         implement something that makes them comfortable.  I have resisted
         providing a complete example script, because I think everyone's setup
         will be different.  However, feel free to write if you are working
         through this and you have questions.
      </para>

   </simplesect>

</appendix>

